Guide to the Plymouth Church of the Pilgrims and Henry Ward Beecher collection, 1819-1980 ARC.212
Brooklyn Historical Society
Plymouth Church of the Pilgrims and Henry Ward Beecher collection
1819-1980
1847-1887
Brooklyn Historical Society
Beecher, Henry Ward
King, Horatio C. (Horatio Collins)
Ellinwood, T. J. (Truman Jeremiah)
Plymouth Church (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
Church of the Pilgrims (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
Plymouth Church of the Pilgrims (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
ARC.212
48.5 Cubic Feet in 75 boxes: 32 manuscript boxes, 38 flat boxes, and 6 small boxes
The Plymouth Church of the Pilgrims and Henry Ward Beecher collection traces the career of the Reverend Henry Ward Beecher, the well known 19th century preacher, and the history of Plymouth Congregational Church, of which Beecher was the first pastor. Plymouth Church was a major institution in 19th century Brooklyn, first gaining recognition on national and international levels as Beecher's pulpit. Beecher was well known for his oratorical ability and for his vocal opposition to slavery and support of the Northern cause during the Civil War. He also spoke out on subjects ranging from women's suffrage and evolution to organized labor and temperance. Beecher was a popular figure despite controversy that surrounded his activities, including a charge of adultery that resulted in a widely reported trial in 1875. The collection relates principally to Beecher's pastorate at Plymouth Church from 1847 until his death in 1887. Other materials, ranging through 1980, concern the church's other pastors and the history of Plymouth Church itself, which consolidated with the Church of the Pilgrims in 1934. The papers provide insight into the church congregation's various activities, illustrate the history of Beecher's influence on his congregation and on 19th century congregationalism, and shed light on both the public and private life of a major American personality of the 19th century.
Related Materials
Other archival materials at Brooklyn Historical Society that relate to this collection are:
Plymouth Church collection (Accession 1986.018), which includes miscellaneous annual reports, manuals, etc.
Church of the Pilgrims collection (Accession 1986.019), which includes miscellaneous programs, directories, etc.
Newell Dwight Hillis papers (Accession 1985.004).
Lyman Abbott letter to L.P. Morton of Columbia Heights (Accession 1986.001).
Brooklyn Historical Society newspaper collection (call number ARC.258) includes issues of The Christian Union, which was edited by Beecher.
Brooklyn Young Republican Club collection (Accession 1977.077), which was compiled by Henry Ward Beecher's son, William C. Beecher.
Richard Salter Storrs papers (call number ARC.082). Storrs was a pastor at Church of the Pilgrims.
Linda Nakdimen papers and Henry Ward Beecher Anniversary photographs (accession 2008.038) contains correspondence between Linda Nakdimen and Stuyvesant "Peter" Barry and Alice Trumbull (Scoville) Barry, the great-great-granddaughter of Henry Ward Beecher. The photographs document the 100th year anniversary celebration of Beecher's death in 1987 and the 150th anniversary celebration of the founding of Plymouth Church in 1997. The newspaper clippings are related to the celebrations and Beecher's life.
BHS also six issues of the Daily Graphic (August-October, 1874) devoted to the Beecher/Tilton trial.
Digital images of Plymouth Church and Beecher held by BHS, beyond those in this collection, can be found by searching BHS's PastPerfect database, available in the library.
Secondary materials in BHS's Library can be found at the following call numbers:
Subject: Church of the Pilgrims. Call number: BX5980. B8 P55
Subject: Plymouth Church. Call number: BX7255. B76 P59
Subject: Plymouth Church of the Pilgrims. Call number: BX7255. B7 P5
Subject: Henry Ward Beecher. Call number: CT275.B4343
Published copies of Beecher's sermons. Call number: BX7233.B44
Materials authored by Newell Dwight Hillis, Lyman Abbott, and additional works by Beecher can be found by executing an author search on Bobcat, BHS's on-line catalog. Some specific useful materials include:
Abbott, Lyman. Henry Ward Beecher/ by Lyman Abbott. Boston: Houghton, Mifflin, and Co., 1903.
Chadwick, John W. Henry Ward Beecher: A Sermon. Boston: George H. Ellis, Publisher, 1887.
A Church In History: The Story of Plymouth's First Hundred Years under Beecher, Abbott, Hillis, Durkee, and Fifield. Brooklyn: Plymouth Church of the Pilgrims, 1949.
Clark, Clifford E., Jr. Henry Ward Beecher: Spokesman for a Middle-Class America. Urbana: University of Illinois Press, 1978.
The Federal Writers' Project (New York). The WPA Guide to New York City: The Federal Writers' Project Guide to New York. New York: Pantheon Books, 1982.
Fox, Richard Wightman. Trials of Intimacy: Love and Loss in the Beecher Tilton Scandel. Chicago: The University of Chicago Press, 1999.
Jackson, Kenneth T., ed. The Encyclopedia of New York City. New Haven: Yale University Press, 1995.
Rugoff, Milton. The Beechers: An American Family in the Nineteenth Century. New York: Harper & Row, Publishers, 1981.
Stiles, Henry R. A History of the City of Brooklyn., Volume 3. Brooklyn: Published by Subscription, 1870.
Thompson, Noyes L. The History of Plymouth Church. New York: G. W. Carleton & Co. 1873.
Waller, Altina L. Reverend Beecher and Mrs. Tilton: Sex and Class in Victorian America. Amherst: University of Massachusetts Press, 1982.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to researchers without restriction.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The bulk of the Plymouth Church of the Pilgrims and Henry Ward Beecher collection was donated to the Brooklyn Historical Society (formerly the Long Island Historical Society) by the church on October 29, 1983. The collection was created by Plymouth Church/Plymouth Church of the Pilgrims to document the history of the two churches as well as Plymouth Church's first pastor, Henry Ward Beecher.
The collection is artificial in that many items, especially those related to Beecher, appear to have been collected and donated over an extended period of time, often by congregants who happened upon materials loosely associated to the famous preacher and his time. The collection includes, for example, souvenirs from the Harriet Beecher Stowe House and memorials of the assassinated President Lincoln. Explicit documentation of the provenance of such items is lacking.
Correspondence regarding the collection during the time it was held at Plymouth Church, written sometime after 1920, outlined a prospective plan for the collection. William Davenport, attorney and member of Plymouth Church, stated in the plan that "countless invaluable records especially of the Bethel S[abbath] S[chool] and Main S[abbath] S[chool] were lost [in the 1920 fire] besides scores of fine photographs, documents and other articles relating to the church's history." Davenport urged the active collection of papers and letters relating to prominent church figures, most notably Henry Ward Beecher, to be "secured,... preserved, and [transcribed]." His successful solicitation is evidenced in the numerous typed transcripts of original documents now found within the collection. In addition he called for the creation of "a card catalog of the books, pamphlets, manuscripts, and so forth." This suggestion was also heeded, and the resulting catalog is now housed by Brooklyn Historical Society.
Scope and Contents
The Plymouth-Beecher collection was donated to the Brooklyn Historical Society (formerly the Long Island Historical Society) by the Plymouth Church of the Pilgrims, where it had been amassed over the years. The collection includes Beecher's own manuscripts as well as materials gathered by the church as reference tools. These materials consist mainly of works written about Beecher, and materials dealing with the church during and after Beecher's tenure. A number of the documents deal primarily with Plymouth Church and secondarily with Beecher and his time. Consequently, the collection proves useful for researchers of Beecher's life and for research of the Plymouth Church community and 19th century Congregationalism. Due to the broad scope of these papers, the collection is identified as the Plymouth Church of the Pilgrims and Henry Ward Beecher collection.
The bulk of the collection relates to Henry Ward Beecher and his time at Plymouth Church, and contains materials relating both to Beecher's life apart from the Church, and Plymouth Church's history apart from Beecher, including documents regarding Beecher's successors. The collection as a whole represents the history of Plymouth Church prior to and following its consolidation with Church of the Pilgrims in 1934 and Beecher's relationship with the church, both in actuality, during his life, and in perception, after his death.
Henry Ward Beecher
The materials found in the first series of the collection are focused on Henry Ward Beecher, and are quite diverse. Beecher's interests and activities were varied, a fact that is reflected within those papers directly concerning him. In addition to the materials regarding his time at Plymouth, other aspects of his life, including his work as an abolitionist, his career as a lecturer, and his personal relationships, are represented. Those sections of the series concentrating on his private life and his work prior to Plymouth are less comprehensive than those relating to Plymouth Church and his public persona.
The Beecher series contains materials illustrative of nearly every aspect of Henry Ward Beecher's life as a member of the clergy, beginning with limited materials relating to his years as a young preacher in Indiana. With his letter of acceptance to Plymouth Church, the collection begins to focus on his time in Brooklyn and his association with Plymouth, the church where he earned his fame.
A substantial portion of the manuscript material is made up of correspondence illustrating his work in Brooklyn, his political concerns, his personal interests, and his relationships with family and friends. Much of Beecher's correspondence deals with the management of his summer home, and illustrates his knowledge of, and concern for, his land. The majority of family correspondence can be found in William Beecher's book of letters received. Included are letters from friends and family members, including William's father, Henry Ward Beecher. Additionally, letters and papers relating to individual family members provide insight into Beecher's personal life as well as his public activities. Substantial correspondence to Beecher criticizing his abolitionism can be found in a scrapbook in the Beecher series.
Beecher's literary works, particularly his sermons, are well represented within the series by a group of hand-written manuscripts, as well as the typescript transcripts made by T.J. Ellinwood, who served as Beecher's stenographer for many years. About twenty-five bound copies of such typescripts with introductory notes by Ellinwood are included in addition to unbound packets. Ellinwood also bound the reviews and correspondence concerning those collections of Beecher's writings published posthumously. In addition to these volumes, the collection contains a substantial representation of pamphlet printings, some quite rare, of Beecher's works, as well as Beecher's sermon notebook.
Records of Beecher's ministry at Plymouth Church are certainly of special note and can be specifically seen in the reminiscences of church members, as well as the large collection of ephemera, record books, and miscellaneous notices documenting the major events in the history and business of the church during Beecher's tenure. Several of these events, such as the "Silver Wedding Celebration" and Beecher's seventieth birthday, focus on Beecher. However, found within the second series of the collection, which focuses on Plymouth Church, are more general church records from Beecher's tenure, such as those of the Sabbath School, along with membership applications and church publications.
Also documented in the Beecher series is his and, in turn, Plymouth's stand on the major issues of the day, namely slavery and the Civil War. Beecher was a prominent figure in the anti-slavery movement and a key supporter of the Union during the War and many in his congregation followed suit. The "auctioning" of slaves in Plymouth Church is related in the materials concerning the enslaved girl, "Pinky," whose name later in life was Rose Ward Hunt. Hunt's return to Plymouth Church in 1927 is documented in the collection, which includes an audio cylinder with brief remarks from Hunt; a digital version of the cylinder recording can be heard in the BHS library. Reactions to Beecher's politics can be seen in a scrapbook of letters he received from his readers throughout the nation and of newspaper clippings about his activities.
The collection includes political material from the war period, which came to the Church through Beecher's political involvement. The controversy over Beecher's support of the military and his relationship with Lincoln are alluded to, and there are letters written by several important political and military figures. Copies of Beecher's famous "Eulogy on Grant" can also be found in the collection, in manuscript as well as published form, along with his "Narrative of Trip to Fort Sumter."
For those specifically interested in Beecher or the moral culture of the day, the collection holds accounts of the Beecher-Tilton adultery trial. Ephemera, two scrapbooks of newspaper clippings, and the five volumes of the official and verbatim trial reports, allow for a thorough study of the trial and the public reaction to these events.
Upon Beecher's death in 1887, numerous memorials and testimonials of his life were published in various newspapers and magazines. The collection holds twelve scrapbooks containing such articles, memorial pamphlets, sermons, speeches, and poems, including an elaborate hand calligraphed memorial album and various memorabilia from Beecher's funeral. Anniversaries of his death were similarly publicized and a number of memorial organizations were founded in his name. The collection holds records of the Beecher Literary and Debating Society and the Beecher Missionary Circle, as well as an article concerning the Beecher Memorial Church, founded in Brooklyn in 1932.
Plymouth Church
The material in the second series of the collection pertain principally to the history of Plymouth Church. Although the bulk of material in this series dates from the death of Henry Ward Beecher in 1887, items from Beecher's tenure at Plymouth Church can be found in much of the series.
The series includes Church Manuals (which include Articles of Faith, Church procedures, and member rosters), Church Bulletins, programs from holiday services, the church's monthly publication, The Plymouth Chimes, and Plymouth Chimes' Calendars. Although the publication runs in the collection are incomplete, the publications do reveal the ideology of the church. The Chimes was not published in July and August, and are in three formats in this collection: bound, oversized and loose. The Plymouth Hymnal: For the Church the Social Meeting and the Home indicates how services should be conducted at Plymouth Church.
There are also a number of church records, including annual reports, a shareholder book (1859), a list of applicants to the church, and charts of pew rental records (1900-1924). Although there are gaps, the annual reports show the financial standing of the Church throughout its history. Other items, such as the subscription book, include names and addresses of those who contributed to the church. In addition, there is a volume of applicants to Plymouth Church (1868-1870). This volume indicates the religious history of the applicant and includes hometown, if the applicant recently moved to the Brooklyn area. The series also contains additional lists indicating members and contributors to the church.
Sunday and Sabbath School materials include rosters and roll books, some of which include the addresses of the students. In addition to these rosters, the activities and operation of the schools are documented through Hymn Books and sheet music from holiday events, scrapbooks, and other ephemera.
The extent to which Plymouth Church involved itself in the Brooklyn Heights community is revealed in materials related to various Church activities, including programs and pamphlets pertaining to the Arbuckle Institute, Plymouth Institute, and Plymouth Church House. These pamphlets and programs indicate the types of activities the Institutes and Church House sponsored. Activities included classes ranging from accounting to physical education and social events, such as concerts and plays. Also found are pamphlets and programs pertaining to other Plymouth organizations such as the Plymouth League and the Plymouth Men's Club. There are also bills, receipts, and account books from several benevolence organizations that were affiliated with the church. Of special interest in this section are the materials relating to the Plymouth Rock Celebration. These items document the organization of the event, from sending out invitations and seeking potential speakers, to thanking participants for their assistance. The low attendance for the event compared to the high expectations for participation in the event, reveals the decline in membership facing the church, even after the consolidation of Plymouth Church and Church of the Pilgrims.
The documentation of Plymouth Church's history also includes material concerning its pastors other than Beecher. Those materials relating to Dr. Lyman Abbott, Beecher's immediate successor, are most closely related to Beecher, documenting life in Brooklyn during the time and noting the continued importance of Beecher's reputation. Each of the succeeding pastors was constantly aware of Plymouth Church being representative of Beecher's legacy, and papers from each show their attention to this fact. In addition, biographical information, clippings, and ephemera pertaining to the pastors are found in this series. The writings of Newell Dwight Hillis are of special note here. Hillis's outspoken view urging the United States to enter World War I and his Better America lecture series, following the War, illustrate his pro-American position during this time of political unrest in the United States.
The Plymouth materials also include correspondence and clippings of noted members of Plymouth Church. The church's continued concern for the reputation of its most famous son can be seen in its stance against Paxton Hibben's 1927 biography of Beecher in this series. The book did not show the minister in the most favorable light and the members of Plymouth gathered clippings and reviews of the spirited responses to it, and engaged in an active letter writing campaign in an attempt to discredit its account. Scrapbooks created by members of the church documenting the activities of the congregation, Henry Ward Beecher, and the Beecher family through newsclippings, programs, bulletins, and other ephemera are in the collection. Items from Church of the Pilgrims prior to its consolidation with Plymouth Church and other miscellaneous items can also be found.
The collection also includes a large number of photographs of Beecher throughout his life, and Plymouth Church of the Pilgrims throughout its history, as well as related scenes and people.
Arrangement
The Plymouth Church of the Pilgrims and Henry Ward Beecher collection is organized in three series:
Series 1: Henry Ward Beecher, 1819-1958
Series 2: Plymouth Church, 1824-1980
Series 3: Images, circa 1840s-circa 1966
The first two series are further arranged into several sections that are described below at the series level. The series contain overlapping dates and materials. For example, those materials recording the daily workings of Plymouth Church during Henry Ward Beecher's tenure, such as Sunday School records, are found within Series 2: Plymouth Church, as their primary function illustrates the activities of the church, not Beecher. Similarly, the records of Beecher's Silver Wedding Anniversary, which, although organized by the church, relate directly to Beecher, are found in Series 1: Henry Ward Beecher.
Date ranges used on folders and for the collection as a whole were determined on a best effort basis within the time constraints of processing. Consequently there may be documents in folders with dates that fall outside the noted date range. This is particularly true for the many scrapbooks, newsclippings, and undated documents in the collection. An effort was made within processing constraints to place a circa date on these.
Biographical / Historical
Plymouth Church of the Pilgrims Chronology
1844 Church of the Pilgrims established
1847 Plymouth Church established; Henry Ward Beecher installed as pastor
1849 Fire destroys Plymouth Church (January)
1850 New church completed (June)
1872 Henry Ward Beecher's Silver Anniversary at Plymouth Church (October)
1887 Death of Beecher; Beecher's funeral at Plymouth Church (March)
1888 Lyman Abbott installed as pastor
1898 Lyman Abbott's resignation announced (Fall)
1899 Newell Dwight Hillis installed as pastor
1902 Henry Ward Beecher Memorial plan instituted
1914 Arbuckle Institute dedicated
1918 Arbuckle Institute renamed Plymouth Institute (December)
1920 Plymouth Church damaged by fire (November)
1922 Death of Lyman Abbott (October 22)
1924 Newell Dwight Hillis disabled by cerebral hemorrhage; resignation announced
1927 James Stanley Durkee installed at Plymouth Church (January 27)
1927 Rose Ward Hunt ("Pinky") returns to Plymouth Church on occasion of 80th anniversary of Beecher's first sermon at Plymouth Church (May 15)
1929 Death of Newell Dwight Hillis (February 25)
1934 Consolidation of Plymouth Church and Church of the Pilgrims (Spring)
1939 Plymouth Institute renamed Plymouth Church House (May)
1940 J. Stanley Durkee's resignation announced (October)
1940 Plymouth Rock Celebration (December 21-23)
1942 L. Wendell Fifield installed at Plymouth Church of the Pilgrims (May 22)
1951 Death of J. Stanley Durkee (September)
1954 L. Wendell Fifield's resignation announced (October)
1955 L. Wendell Fifield leaves Plymouth Church of the Pilgrims (July)
1961 Plymouth Church of the Pilgrims designated Historic Landmark
1964 Death of L. Wendell Fifield (July)
Beecher Chronology
1813 Born, Litchfield, Connecticut; youngest child of Lyman and Roxana Beecher (June 24)
1830 Entered Amherst College
1834 Graduated Amherst College
1834 Began theological studies at Lane Seminary, Cincinnati, Ohio (July)
1837 Graduated Lane Seminary. Began first pastorate at First Presbyterian Church, Lawrenceberg, Indiana
1837 Married Eunice White Bullard of Massachusetts
1838 First daughter, Harriet Eliza, born (May 16)
1838 Ordained at First Presbyterian Church, Lawrenceberg, Indiana (November 9)
1839 Installed at Second Presbyterian Church, Indianapolis, Indiana (July 31)
1841 Son, Henry Barton Beecher, born
1847 Resigned from Indianapolis pastorate (August 15)
1847 Accepted call to Plymouth Church, Brooklyn (August 19)
1847 Installed at Plymouth Church (November 11)
1848 First mock slave auction at the Broadway Tabernacle, New York City (December 7)
1849 Plymouth Church destroyed by fire (January 13)
1850 Departed on first trip to Europe (July 9)
1850 New church completed according to Beecher's design (January)
1856 Slave girl, Sarah, sold for her freedom at Plymouth Church (June 1)
1856 Leave of absence taken from Plymouth to campaign for the election of John C. Fremont as President
1858 Great Revival at Plymouth Church
1859 Farm purchased in Peekskill, New York
1860 Enslaved girl Sally Maria Diggs, "Pinky," (a.k.a. Rose Ward) auctioned for freedom (February)